<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Trappan trapt. Or The true relation of a cunning, cogging, confident, crafty, counterfeit, cosening and cheating knight, alias knave. Wherein is discovered his mischievous and Machivillian matchlesse mischeefs, plotted against an honest gentleman, a marchant of good repute, named Mr Iohn Marriot: dwelling neer London Bridge. Set forth for the benfit of others, who else through ignorance might easily fall into the like snares of such dissembling, vvicked, and trecherous Trappans. By W.B.</title>
            <author>W. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B232</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E910_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207497</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866544</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866544</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118820</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76531)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118820)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 137:E910[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Trappan trapt. Or The true relation of a cunning, cogging, confident, crafty, counterfeit, cosening and cheating knight, alias knave. Wherein is discovered his mischievous and Machivillian matchlesse mischeefs, plotted against an honest gentleman, a marchant of good repute, named Mr Iohn Marriot: dwelling neer London Bridge. Set forth for the benfit of others, who else through ignorance might easily fall into the like snares of such dissembling, vvicked, and trecherous Trappans. By W.B.</title>
                  <author>W. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Joseph Moxon, and sold at his shop on Corn-hill, at the sign of Atlas,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 4".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriot, John, --  merchant --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118820:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The TRAPPAN Trapt. OR The true Relation of a Cunning, Cogging, Confident, Crafty, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, Coſening and Cheating KNIGHT, <hi>alias</hi> KNAVE.</p>
            <p>Wherein is Diſcovered his Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous and Machivillian matchleſſe Miſcheefs, Plotted againſt an Honeſt Gentleman, a Marchant of good Repute, named Mr <hi>Iohn Marriot:</hi> Dwelling neer LONDON BRIDGE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Set forth for the benefit of Others, who elſe through Ignorance might eaſily fall into the like ſnares of ſuch Diſſembling, VVicked, and Trecherous</hi> TRAPPANS.</p>
            <p>By W. B.</p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by <hi>Joſeph Moxon,</hi> and ſold at his Shop on Corn-hill, at the Sign of
<hi>Atlas.</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:118820:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118820:2"/>
            <head>The TRAPPAN Trapt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is too apparently evidenced by ſad experience, that a Civil War draws a longer train or tail behind it, then any other inconvenience whatſoever, that can come or happen on a Common-wealth; for the miſerable conſequences there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, are not ſheathed with the bloody-drawn ſword; nor do the effects ceaſe, though the cauſe matter and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner are withdrawn from the face and body of action, as may plainly appear by the truths in the inſuing diſcourſe, ſetting forth a perfect relation of the Cheating or Trappanning courſes, taken by the pretenders to worth and honourable imployment; as did this ſubject of our Hiſtory now in hand: One <hi>Francis Moor,</hi> an Iriſh man, who pretended that he had been a Collonel, in the late King of <hi>England's</hi> ſervice, an imployment long ſince caſhiered the honour of memory; yet this Gallant continues himſelf in the Liſt; and doth not only make that a Cloak to cover his ſpecious preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of undertaking action of great concernment; but to add a fair gloſs to the glory of his pretended ingagements, Laces that Cloak about with a more glitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cognizance, and in his own defence; dubbs himſelf Knight, under the noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and title of Sir
<hi>Francis Barker</hi> of <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> and under the ſhadow (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with another ſhell to dreſs his Knight-hood or knavery in <hi>viz.</hi> Dr. <hi>Barker</hi> Doctor of phyſick, he not only deludes, cheats, and abuſes the plainer ſort of honeſt people; but reaches to very dead (I mean in the late King) whoſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is in nothing more queſtionable then in the imployment of ſuch ignoble ſpirits to act by his Commiſſion, nor doth it yet ſtick there; but as it were a deſign laid on purpoſe to bring a perpetual ignominy on that ſad and enough abuſed family by ſuch Villans, who will be ſure to make the King of
<hi>Scots</hi> the Patron of their wickedneſs. There is ſcarce a notorious piece of Debauchery
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118820:3"/>acted; but the contrivers are reputed or reported (by themſelves) to be people imployed for him; and indeed this is not all, but that which they think will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more Roguery, then all the Kings in the World, they are not aſhamed to ſtigmatize the Army, and Common-wealth of <hi>England;</hi> with pretences of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been, nay immediately to be Officers or Members of this now Army; to carry on their divelliſh deſigns, as this <hi>Pſeudo</hi> Cavalier, Sir
<hi>Marmaduke</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny forms hath done; when (as formerly) he durſt lie about the City of
<hi>London;</hi> ſometimes pretending the receit of great Arrears; ſometimes a great imploiment from the Lord Protector, to deceive and delude poor people, and make himſelf ſeem the more creditable in the eye of the World; as he did ſome two yeers ſince, at one Mr. <hi>Godbids</hi> an honeſt Tradeſmans houſe in <hi>Red-Croſſe</hi> ſtreet in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> where one while he was one of the Armies Officers; another time (as he found the diſpoſition of people he had commerce withall a diſtreſſed Gentleman a Cavalier, and one that had ſuffered very much loſſe in his eſtate by the common enemy (Civil War) as being a Collonel for the King; but when theſe Viſards began to be pretty well worn out, and fearing leſt his own face ſhould appear through in its proper colours, he takes on another more dark and full of amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than any of the reſt. And ſaid he was ſon to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> (which they might be the more apt to beleeve, becauſe he had ſuch an incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable uſe and benefit of his French tongue, which he ſpake as abſolutely as a Native French-man) and ſayes (which is alwaies his great <hi>aſſilum</hi> in ſuch extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, when nothing elſe will gloſs his falſities) that he had fought a Duel with a grand favourite of <hi>France,</hi> and was ſo perſecuted in Law for his preſumption, and diſobedience for the King, Orders (having then newly made and ſet forth an Edict againſt Duels) that he was inforced to take <hi>England</hi> for his ſhelter, and though for the preſent hee ſeemed ſomewhat ſtraitned for want of due ſupplies of monies (which he ſaid was occaſioned by his ſudden flight) yet his mother who (as he heard) indeavoured with all her power and powerfull friends to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his pardon from the King) would not fail to ſend him all the ſpeedieſt and neceſſary returns for ſupply, that ſhould be imagined fit for a perſon of his qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as ſoon as ſhe did underſtand where he was; and therefore pretended often to write Letters of advice into <hi>France,</hi> and to receive diſpatches from thence, with promiſes of Bills for monies very ſuddenly; till at laſt with theſe and the like inſinuations he had involved himſelf ſo far into his honeſt Landlords pith and good opinion, that he became a Fauciliſt, and at bed and board promiſing (at leaſt propoſing a cate of ſeven ſhillings <hi>per</hi> week an eaſie cate for a young Duke, was entertained by his new Hoſt, as his brother or ſon, and then after a little time was viſited by many great Gallants of much ſeeming worth and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, who (but Ile warrant you by his own advice und order) for the moſt part ſtood alwaies at great diſtance, and all bare-headed, giving him as much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance and reſpect, as if he had been the real Duke himſelf, which confirmed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118820:3"/>the honeſt people in their miſ-beleef, and himſelf in an imaginary Dukedom. Yet becauſe he would not ſeem to be what they thought he was would diſmount himſelf from that garb of glory which he ſeemed to be in, when the people held him in ſuch adoration, and would vouchſafe ſome of them to his familiarity, they muſt ſtay and keep him company, dine with him and paſſe away the time after dinner with drinking a glaſſe or two of Wine, whereof there was no want; for the young Duke could ſcarcely drink any thing but wine; which at firſt, himſelf would often ſend money for; but afterwards there was ſuch an intimacy of friendſhip and familiarity between the Hoſt and his Gueſt, that it was no more but Landlord, I ſhall have ſuch and ſuch friends come to dine with me to day, pray ſend for ſo many bottles of Wine, which was without ſcruple performed; and thus by degrees increaſed his credit, and his ſcore very handſomly with his Landlord, and his whole family, but not ſo fully as he thought fit, til he had poſſeſt his good Creditor, (remembring his haſty flight,) that he had left his Clothes behind, and therfore deſires his Credit and aſſiſtance to equip him in Engliſh <hi>A la mode France;</hi> and this began to be the winding up of his bottom there. His Landlord not doubting but his young Duke would prove a Prince in time, would not let him want any thing he deſired, Eſpecially ſuch things as might ſet him forth like himſelfe, and therefore with his purſe and Credit furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed him with good ſtore of gold and ſilver lace, and other hanſome furniture, till the ſumma totalis amounted to 220 <abbr>
                  <hi>lb.</hi>
               </abbr> all which the Duke was in his Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords debt, and ſomething too from one ſquire
<hi>Fiſher</hi> of <hi>Glouceſterſhire</hi> who lay then in the ſame houſe.</p>
            <p>But now to pay our Landlord and give a general ſatisfaction to all, one Tueſday morning he comes to his Landlords bed ſide, Well Landlord (quoth he) I am going to fetch money for you: (having often enough and ſufficiently promiſed it before.) I Sir replyed his Landlord I hope you win. Nay ſays the young Spark, I have received my Bills, and they being accepted, I am going to receive my money but if I do not receive it (by God quoth he) I will ſell this ſame to pay you (ſhewing him a very noble Diamond Ring, to any bodies thinking,) which he wore on his finger, which ſeemed of an immenſe valew: (as indeed it was, being worth above halfe his Dukedome: and ſo takeing a morning (or rather a mourning farwell) of them away he goes, leaving in his Chamber his Trunks, (which they doubted not was full of the rich clothes ſo lately made for his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor:) but in brief my Gentleman was ſo overladen with his money that he could not come home againe that night, nor indeed the next day: when in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone his Landlord and his wife fearing and doubting the Truth, made bold to inquire into his Trunkes, where they found the Neſt, but the Birds flowns wherefore he muſt now bethink him what to doe; and then remembring that ſurely his mother would not be unmindfull of ſuch a hopefull young gentelman as her ſon, but had ere this procured his Pardon, which he having notice of, was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118820:4"/>gone to take the benefit of: and therefore preſently poſts away his ſon after him, who together with another freind of his, haſted by Graveſend, and that night poſted towards <hi>Dover;</hi> by the way often hearing of him: and to Dover they Perſue him but there <hi>Ne plus ultra,</hi> for <hi>Monſieur</hi> was gone for Callis on wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day by noone, and ſo the youngſter may returne to Certify his freindes in London: where we leave him to tell his ſtrange adventures in the perſuite, and his father with time enough to ſumme up his bookes of his gueſts ingagement, and returne to the <hi>Monſieur,</hi> whom wee finde in France glittering in his new Cloths and honor, which will there ſtand him in no ſteed: wherefore he thinkes it more convenient to change his French Honor, for Engliſh Worſhip, and intitles himſelf Sir <hi>Francis Barker</hi> of Staffordſhire Knight, which now ſuites beſt to his purpoſe. And ſo in May laſt, he makes a voyage to London, where we will diſpenſe with him for a while, and let him alone in his Inne, plotting and Contriving diverſe ſtratagems; and meet with one Mr <hi>William Marriot,</hi> living neer London Bridge, a Marchant of very good account among all men of his owne ranke and dealing, a very honeſt, ſober, quiet, iuſt, religious, plaine man in all his dealings in the world and the generall eſteem of all that knew him; and by this Character you may know him to be no Cunning ſnapp in worldly matters; and therefore the leſſe able to judge when hee met with ſuch an one; and this honeſt ſimplicity rendred him the more eaſy to be betrayed by any ſuch knave, as ſought to delude the honeſt: and what made him more lyable to be wrought upon, (though he were a man that dealt much abroad in the world,) Could neither read nor write, but truſted all accounts for Trades, (of which he had many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſeas) either to the recordes of other mens pens or his owne Marke and memory; and in this manner had Commerce with all ſortes of people for a long time: till at laſt this M. <hi>William Marriott</hi> having imployed divers Factors in France, and chiefly in Roven, where lay the greateſt part of his Trade, and ſtock, and had often ſent letters, to demand an account of his eſtate there, in their handes; as being ſo Carefull and provident, that his eſtate ſhould not be waſted and imbeziled by the improvidence of others, which he did endeavor to to preſerve and ſtrengthen, for the future maintainance of himſelfe and family.</p>
            <p>But letters were but words, and words but wind, wich blew no good to Mr <hi>Mariott</hi> as he thought for they brought him no news of his Eſtate, nor account from his Factors but delatory putt offs and nothing to the purpoſe Wherefore (on good Conſideration and adviſe of Friends.) Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> reſolves that he will himſelf take a Iourney into France, to Compell them to give an account of their Stewardſhip or at leaſt to take into his own hands, what he ſhould there find belonging to him, before all was gone. And ſo on the 30 th. of <hi>May</hi> laſt 1656. he took horſe at the <hi>Spurre</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> intending to go for
<hi>Rye</hi> in <hi>Suffex,</hi> where at the ſame inſtant, he that Called himſelf Sir
<hi>Francis Barker</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd, tooke horſe too; and pretending the ſame Journey, imediately rides
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118820:4"/>out of the Inn with him; telling him in the mean time, that he was bound for France, and ſhould be very glad of good Company; which to Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> ſeemed no leſſe then a bleſſing beyond Expectation, in regard Sir <hi>Francis</hi> (as he called himſelf) promiſed by all probable Conjectures to be an abſolute Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and nothing Leſſe then what that outward Garb had promiſed, and his inward parts (whereof he had by this time given many gracefull teſtimoneys,) to be ſuch that might have been a Cabinet for Concerns of the greateſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences. Beſides his moſt exellent knowledge and delivery of the French tongue, (the cheifeſt Iewel in all his Treaſury,) for Mr <hi>Marriotts</hi> uſe, who could neither ſpeak nor underſtand the leaſt breath of the French Dialect. Theſe noble endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo wrought on Mr <hi>Marriotts</hi> honeſt Iudgement, that he preſently thought his new acquaitance to be a man fit to open his breaſt to: And to be ſhort both being mounted, acquainted, and reſolved for the ſame Journey, away they ride; and already we find them a Lighting at the ſigne of the <hi>Anchor</hi> in <hi>Rye,</hi> a little By-houſe of Entertainment, where our Knight was well acquainted and reſpected, (having it ſeemes,) uſed this houſe for many years before; becauſe he had frequently, (it may be) on the like occaſions paſſed betweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France:</hi> here the courteous Knight gallantly welcome the Diſconſolate Squire, and entertains him with ſuch a feaſt of his own good Company, that they were very freely merry, and in that mirth had ſo Confirmed and Contracted their new acquaintance that they muſt (as it were) go both under one hood; for Sir
<hi>Francis</hi> muſt Call him nothing but Father, and Mr <hi>Marriott</hi> from that time forward muſt Call him Son, and a forfeiture under a certain penalty to be paid by him that ſhould at any time hereafter forget the duty or indulgency of Son, or Father. Thus this new adopted Father and Sonne take Sea, and within few hours Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at <hi>Deip</hi> in
<hi>France.</hi> By this time Sir <hi>Francis</hi> Like a dutifull Sonne was ſo diligent, and indulgent that he had carefully dived into his Fathers debt 6. or 7. foot (Pounds I ſhould ſay) deep. But <hi>Deip</hi> they leave, and in ſhort ſpace arive at <hi>Roven;</hi> where Sir
<hi>Francis</hi> brings his Father to the <hi>Boon Foy,</hi> an Inn where the Son was very well acquainted, and in the French tongue at large inquired all affaires and news: but the Father ſeems more a Child, that ſate all this while and opened not his mouth, but minding his buſineſs he came about, more then the Curioſities of <hi>France</hi> for the preſent, hee deſired his good Sonne Sir <hi>Francis</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake the paines as to goe with him, and inquire out his Factors, which the Sonne moſt obediently condiſcended to; and together they go to the Factors where Mr <hi>Marriott</hi> demanding an account, they preſently ſhow what they have received,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd what moneys they have drawn upon thoſe goods; as like wiſe the reſidue as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et not ſold: all which Sir <hi>Francis</hi> Caſt up, for Mr <hi>Marriott</hi> (as I told you) could neither write nor read; but Committed all to memory: and by the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccount finds there was 1000
<abbr>
                  <hi>lb.</hi>
               </abbr> good to Mr <hi>Marriot;</hi> 200. thereof was ready
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Bank, when Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> pleaſed ſo Command the ſame; which was very
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118820:5"/>much to his content. And now Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> (ſeeing all things were ſo well there,) would needs have his wife and friends in <hi>England,</hi> (that were partakers of his former doubts,) be ſhaters in his preſent ſatiſfaction and content: and to that purpoſe deſires Sir <hi>Francis</hi> to be now his Secretarie, and write ſome Letters for him to his wife in <hi>London,</hi> to acquaint her and the reſt of his freinds there, of his preſent Eſtate of health, and good ſucceſs he had hitherto had in his Journey; which was all Sir
<hi>Francis</hi> deſired, that he might the more eaſily dive into his Fathers ſecrets; and unſuſpected diſcover, what he reſolves now to be Maſter of; viz. his Eſtate.</p>
            <p>But in ſome of theſe letters he informed them, that Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> (whom they knew well enough to be an honeſt, Godly, plain man, but no diſputant;) held high diſputes in diſcourſe with the Papiſh Preiſts, and argued with them in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies of Religion; That he did fear they would do him ſome ſudden miſcheif, and therefore adviſed them that in their next letters to Mr <hi>Marriot,</hi> they would Councell him to forbear Speaking, or diſputeing with thoſe (as he rightly enough tearmed them.) Bloody Revengers.</p>
            <p>This was the firſt Scean of the Tragedy he intended to Plot on the ſtage or Mr
<hi>Marriots</hi> Ruine; and this was done that after he had performed the bloody Tragady himſelf of his fathers Death and Ruine, that then the loſſe and miſhap that had fallen on Mr
<hi>Marriot</hi> ſhould have been layd to theſe Prieſts account: for indeed no body knew any elſe to accuſe. But herein we only give a gueſſe at his intent, and I think a ſhrowd one too.</p>
            <p>But to proceed to my ſtory, after this loving Father and precious Son, had ſtayed ſome 10 dayes in <hi>Roven,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis</hi> would needes perſwade his Father <hi>Marriot</hi> to ſome recreation, and to take ſo much pleaſure of his Journey as to go up to
<hi>Paris,</hi> and to ſee ſo much of that <hi>City,</hi> that when he returned he might report ſo much of the Country and place, that might reader him more like a Traveler, then a meſſenger or Carryer, that could onely ſay <hi>There I have beene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> Conſidering that his buſines was in a pretty good decorum, and his friends in <hi>England</hi> had advertiſement thereof, ſo that they need not be in ſuſpence of his welfare; and withall thinking himſelf a litle ingaged to Sir <hi>Francis</hi> for his aſſiſtance in <hi>Roven,</hi> would not be ſuch a Churle, as to deny him ſo cheap a courteſy, and therfore condiſcended to bear his Son company to <hi>Paries</hi> And with this reſolution away they go to <hi>Paris;</hi> where Sir <hi>Francis</hi> brings his Father to his own houſe, in the <hi>Toubour Saint German,</hi> where there was a French woman that lay with Sir
<hi>Francis:</hi> and by whom he had formerly had a child or a but was never married to her. Here Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> was very well reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for ſome dayes, though at his own Coſt, and nothing was wanting that might not make him think, nay aſſure himſelf he was wellcom: For beſides the generall obſervance that he had from all perſons in or belonging to the houſe, his Sonne Sir <hi>Francis</hi> would in no wiſe be thought flack, in his duty; but dayly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118820:5"/>attended on his Father up and down <hi>Paris,</hi> every where feeding his eye with ſeverall varieties of houſes Gardens walks and ſuch pleaſant proſpects, whereof
<hi>Paris</hi> is plentifully full. But, that which is herein chiefly to be taken notice of, in all theſe tranſactions, you muſt obſerve Sir <hi>Francis</hi> did not permit his Father to come into any Engliſh Company, or to have any Converſe with any that had but a peece of an Engliſh tongue; except himſelf: neither did Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> diſtruſt any thing of danger, although he had all this while about him, a letter from a Merchant in <hi>London,</hi> to deliver to an Engliſh Gentleman in <hi>Paris;</hi> which Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> (in caſe he did not go to
<hi>Paris</hi> himſelf) was to ſend thither from <hi>Roven.</hi> But being now in
<hi>Paris,</hi> at laſt he ſhews it to his Son Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> deſireing him to read the ſuperſcription, and direct him to find out the Gent. which Sir <hi>Francis</hi> grants, but reads no more of the ſuperſcription then thus; <hi>For Mounſeur Bond in Paris:</hi> though the ſuperſcription was very large and ſufficient, (as ſhall hereafter in this diſcourſe ſufficiently appeate,) and preſently, Peugh (quoth he) is this all, what foole was he that wrote this directions? he had as good have written, <hi>For Mounſeur Bond</hi> in France, and as ſoon they ſhould have found him. So Sir <hi>Francis</hi> put the letter in his owne Pocket, with a kind of a ſleight put off, or indeed put up. But Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> being loth to lett it ſo ſlip, through his ſlippery fingers; repleyed, Nay, (quoth he,) good Son give mee the letter again; that ſo I may ſhow it to the party, and not only by his own eyes Convince him of his error; but laugh at him for his folly, which Sir <hi>Francis</hi> could not with modeſty deny, but with a ſeeming willingneſs gave his Father <hi>Marriot</hi> the letter.</p>
            <p>Thus having paſſed away ſome 10 dayes in <hi>Paris,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis</hi> comes to his Father, tells him he hath ſome very urgent buſines, at a Town Called <hi>Corbell,</hi> ſome 7 or 8 leagues from <hi>Paris</hi> by water; there to meet with a Gentelman, a ſpeciall loving friend of his, who had lately fought (as he ſaid) a Duell about <hi>Paris,</hi> and therfore durſt not yet come any nerer: however he was imediately imployed by the King of Scots, and that he had brought ſome letters from the ſaid King to Sir <hi>Francis;</hi> ſo that if Mr
<hi>Marriot</hi> would go down with him to <hi>Corbell,</hi> he ſhould there heare all the News of affaires, with the ſaid King; and furniſh himſelf with News enough to carry home with him, when he went; which might be as ſoon as Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> pleaſed, for that (as Sir
<hi>Francis</hi> told him) they would come backe again, either the ſame night, or the next morning at furtheſt.</p>
            <p>Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> (who was much delighted with his new ſons good Company.) thought, for ſo little a time it would be uncivil to leave him therfore would not give his good Son a deniall; but away preſently they go, and without ſword or ſticke, or any other ſort
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mes, put themſelves into a boate together: and Sir <hi>Francis</hi> his pretended
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in Law in their Company, which was the Father of the forementioned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whom Sir <hi>Francis</hi> cald wife, and with in ſhorte
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118820:6"/>ſpace they land ſafe at <hi>Corbell</hi> but there was no ſuch man there, as Sir <hi>Francis</hi> had formerly ſpoken of. But Sir <hi>Francis</hi> (becauſe he would not be much obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to walk about the town with M. <hi>Marriot</hi> as he had formerly been at
<hi>Paris,</hi>) poſſeſſes the honeſt miſtruſtleſs Gentelman (Mr <hi>Marriot,</hi>) that the expected Gentelman ſtayd for him at a private houſe, a matter of a mile and half, or 2 miles out of the town, whether he muſt go to ſpeak with him: ſtill perſwading Mr
<hi>Marriot,</hi> that this Gentelman and himſelf carried on buſineſſes of immence concerments concerning the King of Scotts. Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> was eaſily induced to beleeve all this; and as eaſily ſeduced to go along with them: and having taken ſuch a tedious Journey by water, would not ſtick now to walk a mile or two by land; partly for his own recreation, and partly to ſatisfy the importunity of his Son Sir <hi>Francis;</hi> who told him, that this was the period of all his buſines in France; and this diſpatched, he would then be at his Fathers diſpoſe, if he pleaſed, to wait on him back again, even into England: which Mr
<hi>Marriot</hi> was not a little glad of, in regard of the ſtrangeneſſe of the place, people and language, (to him utterly unknowne) and therfore, (without any great ſcruple) went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with him to the promiſed place, which Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> found private indeed; being a lone houſe, in the midſt of many great Vinyards, and large Corn fields, not any houſe neer it by 2 miles at leaſt, the nereſt was <hi>Corbell;</hi> Neither was here any accomodation, but what ſatisfyed a poor old man and woman, who merely dwelt there to look to the Vinyards: yet here they ſtayd till it was now almoſt night, but no Gentelman from the King of Scots, to our brave Knight: ſo ſayes Mr <hi>Marriot,</hi> Come Son let us return to the Town, and lodge there this night, for here is not any accomodation, but at the Town we may refreſh our ſelves at our pleaſure, and be here again to morrow; but this adviſe ſuited not with Sir <hi>Francis</hi> his ſtratagems: wherfore he replyed, No No, Father, we will even make as good ſhift as we can, with theſe honeſt folkes this night, in this houſe, (which though it ſeem very bad, I muſt tell you the King of England hath been contented with a worſe) and my friend, will be with us betimes in the morning. Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> (having no mind to ſtay,) conſidering the lonen-nes of the place, the barreneſs of the houſe, and the ſtrange and uncouth condition of the people, would fain have perſwaded his Son <hi>Francis</hi> to have gone to the Town: but Mr
<hi>Marriots</hi> mouth was quickly ſtopd again, with the King of England &amp;c. and the like put-offs till night came on, and there they muſt be forced to ſtay: where at length there was a bed made where they both lay till day light next morning; when on a ſudden Sir <hi>Francis</hi> ſlides out of the bed, and was making himſelf ready, which made Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> ask him what was the reaſon he roſe up ſo early, it being yet not paſt 3 of the Clock. Father (quoth Sir <hi>Francis</hi>) I was loath to waken you, but I muſt riſe to ſend a meſſenger for my friend to come to me; and then we will be gone toward <hi>Paris.</hi> This new lodging pleaſed not Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> ſo well, that he would ly and take a napp in the morning
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118820:6"/>but (being weary of his Quarters) up he gets, and as he was making himſelf ready, he looked out at the window, where he ſaw his Son Sir <hi>Francis</hi> talking with 3 ſturdy villaines, (all ſtanding bare headed before his worſhip,) but what they ſayd Mr
<hi>Marriot</hi> Could not underſtand; for they ſpoke altogether in French. This made Mr
<hi>Marriot</hi> begin to diſtruſt a little Villany in his Son <hi>Franck;</hi> and therefore began alſo to Conſider with himſelf what to do. But to put thoſe troubles out of his thoughts at the very inſtant up ſtaires comes his dear Son, and his three God-fathers, with each a good ſower Cudgel in his hand, with him; and then Sir <hi>Francis</hi> goes to imbrace and kiſs his Father <hi>Marriot,</hi> ſaying Good Father be not afrayd, there ſhall not an hair of your head be wronged; onely you muſt ſtay here as my Priſoner, till you have payd me 800
<abbr>lb.</abbr> either from <hi>Roven</hi> or <hi>London;</hi> becauſe I am to raiſe a Regiment for my Maſter the King of Scots, (there is He brought in to father his damnable villanies) and I know you are a man of ſuch abilities that you may well ſpare him ſuch a ſum, hee will pay you again: and this you muſt do before you go. Nevertheleſſe you ſhall not want any accomodation befitting your Condition, for I will uſe you as a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, therfore be not afrayd. Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> knew not what anſwere to make him at the preſent, but after a very little deliberation (quoth he) Sir <hi>Francis</hi> you know very well how my eſtate lyes at <hi>Roven,</hi> how the moſt part of my goods ſold are at 3 moneths and 5 moneths payment; and the greateſt part of them are yet unfold, inſomuch that no money can be ſo ſpeedily got in: you know there is 200 <abbr>lb.</abbr> ready in <hi>Roven,</hi> and if you will be contented with that and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge mee, I will make it over to you, (quoth Mr <hi>Marriot.</hi>) This was nothing to Sir <hi>Francis</hi> purpoſe, and therfore he took from his Father <hi>Marriot</hi> a Silver ſtamp of his name, which he did uſe to ſet to all Letters, Acquittances, and Contracts of dealing, and was ever known to be ſufficient Teſtimony of his act and deed; and ſo writ letters preſently to <hi>Roven,</hi> to Mr <hi>Marriots</hi> Factors, affirming this his mark to them to affirm the truth of their Contents, wherein he bids them go to one <hi>Bromwells</hi> veſſell that lay in <hi>Roven,</hi> who had brought divers Goods of his in her, from
<hi>England,</hi> with a Box of wearing Clothes, which Sir <hi>Francis</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to be broken open, and a new ſuit and Cloak of Exellent good Cloth trimed richly with Gold, and a Riding Coat all new, to be ſent imediately for <hi>Paris,</hi> and orders them and all letters, and the like concerning Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> to be directed to <hi>Paris,</hi> in the <hi>Foubour Saint German</hi> to a Lute makers houſe: the like direction he gives to his friends in
<hi>England,</hi> ſo that now what ever letters muſt come for Mr <hi>Marriot,</hi> muſt (unknown to him) be ſent to <hi>Paris;</hi> and by theſe means directly to Sir <hi>Francis</hi> his hands firſt: by which plott Sir <hi>Francis</hi> receives and anſweres Mr <hi>Marriots</hi> letters without his knowledge or leaſt manner of ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition: and this he had ordered a good while before he had ſecured Mr <hi>Marriot.</hi> This happened on Satturday the 21 of Iune 1656. on which day Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> had ſent his pretended Father in law to <hi>Paris,</hi> to receive and bring to him Letters
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118820:7"/>that were that day to come from <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Roven</hi> to Mr
<hi>Marriot,</hi> as Sir <hi>Francis</hi> had appointed them. Then after 3 hours ſtay that the fellows had made (ſtill cloſe attending on them,) Sir <hi>Francis</hi> bids them go to worke in the Vinyard, (which was iuſt by the houſe) and to be within call, which they did; Therby preſuming he kept Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> in aw enough: and then ſends the woman of the houſe to
<hi>Corbell,</hi> to buy proviſion for the next day, (being Sunday) and to bring Wine along with her. At length all being abſent but the Father and Son. Come ſays Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> Father let us go play at Cards to paſſe away the Time, and ſo pulls a pair of new Cards out of his pockett, with which they plaid ſome 2. or. 3. hours, ſtill expecting the return of the woman; for they were very thirſty, and had no manner of drink in the houſe. So ſays Mr
<hi>Marriot</hi> Come ſon, Pray let us not ſit ſtenching up our ſelves within doors, but walk abroad into the Vineyard, and take the freſh air a little, for I am very weary with playing at cards: which Sir <hi>Francis</hi> would faine have put off; for he was very unwilling to truſt himſelf with Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> abroad, there being many other people at work in the Vineyard, beſide the 3 Rogues that were his aſſiſtants: ſo that Sir <hi>Francis</hi> told him they would walk into the fields toward <hi>Corbell</hi> to meet the woman, and ſo come back again with her. Thus Sir <hi>Francis</hi> taking a good Crabbtree Cudgell in his hand, (Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> having none) forth they go, Sir <hi>Francis</hi> always Carrying the Cudgell in the Contray hand to Mr <hi>Marriot,</hi> who had much to do to draw his graceleſs ſon a quarter of a mile from the houſe; at length Mr <hi>Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot</hi> ſtaying behind to make water, overtakes Sir
<hi>Francis</hi> but ſeizing on that ſide where the Cudgell was, he wreſted it out of his hands; and before Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> could recover it to give him a blow therewith, was Sir
<hi>Francis</hi> on his knees, asking his Father bleſſing and pardon, confeſſing his fault, and begging his life, deſiring that he would not kill him: wich made Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> to forbear ſtriking him: and told him that as he had ſaved his life in the morning, ſo he would now give him his: but on this condition, that he Sir <hi>Francis</hi> ſhould return again to the houſe, and not follow him towards <hi>Corbell:</hi> for if he did, he vowed he would kill him, and throw him into the Corn; of which Conditions Sir <hi>Francis</hi> was ſo much overjoyed with; that he deſired his Father (as he ſtill called him) to Pardon him, and ſeal it with a kiſſe, as he was on his knees: which Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> did: and ſo they parted: wherefor this time we muſt leave him to ſhift among his rogues, and follow Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> to the town, where we find him Iuſt entred.</p>
            <p>Here Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> endeavors all he can to find out himſelf, for he was at an Extream loſſe, he knew not what to make of any body, and no body knew what to make of him; for he could ſpeak never a word of <hi>French;</hi> nor they could underſtand nere a word of Engliſh: yet he Continued making of ſignes, and crying out <hi>Angletorre,</hi> which he took to be French enough for one man to be known by; ſo that ſome (perceiving him to bee a ſtranger,) went and Called a Cappuchine an <hi>Italian</hi> born, but one that underſtood <hi>Engliſh</hi> very well; To
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118820:7"/>whom Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> relates his ſad Condition, and tells the whole ſtory: who being a man that wore not the habit only, but had the true ſpirit and Charity of a man in Religious orders, not onely ſtood in admiration at the impious villany of the treacherous knight, but like a pittifull and Compaſſionate Father, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trives which way to relieve the poor diſtreſſed Gentelman in his ſo deplorable Condition, and preſerve him from the future dangers he was incident to, by the treachery of his wicked ſon, and his Complices: and therfore he carries him firſt to his Convent, where the reſt of the Fathers at the relation of the ſtory, are in no leſs wonder then their Brother, nor leſſe Compaſſionate. At length the good <hi>Italian</hi> got a boat for Mr <hi>Marriot,</hi> and bargained with them for 14. ſhillings to ſet him ſafe on ſhore at <hi>Paris;</hi> which carefully was performed by the
2 boate men. But being arived, he was in as great a ſtrait as he was at his coming to
<hi>Corbell;</hi> for he knew not any perſon there, neither could he ſpeak to any to be underſtood; but getting up into the high ſtreet, had recourſe to his former helps at
<hi>Corbell,</hi> viz. making ſignes, and crying out <hi>Angleter Angleter;</hi> and all to as little purpoſe as before; till at laſt a poor <hi>Iriſh</hi> man coming by, and hearing him to inquire for the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> went to him and aſked him what he would give him, and he would bring him to ſome <hi>Engliſh?</hi> Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> was as ready to give, as the other to aſk, and inſteed of 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> which the <hi>Iriſh</hi> man aſked, for his pains, Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> gave him a peice of French money 15
<abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> peice with which being ſo well ſatiſfyed, he Carryes him to the houſe of the <hi>Engliſh Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictines</hi> in the <hi>Foubour Saint Jaques.</hi> To whom Mr
<hi>Marriot</hi> (ſeeing they were men) again relate, the whole ſtory of the unfortunate Father, and unhappy ſon, from the firſt to the laſt, even till he had brought himſelf in there amongſt them, and now deſires them to get him a lodging amongſt ſome
<hi>Engliſh:</hi> which imedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly they do; and leave him that night to his repoſe: but in the morning they ſend their ſervant to him, to bring him to them again, there to be with them till ſome means might be found for his ſafety, or ſome friend or acquaintance of his found out, that would take care to reconvey him back to <hi>Roven</hi> to his factors or elſewhere, out of the danger of his dangerous Son <hi>Francis,</hi> which yet in the ey of Good men ſeemed to threaten him. Here Mr <hi>Marriot</hi> ſhowes the forementioned letter directed to <hi>Mounſeur Bond,</hi> whoſe ſuperſcription they read to him, thus, <hi>For Mounſeur Bond, Controuler of the Queen of Englands houſe, in the Pallace Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in the Rue Saint Onory at Paris.</hi> Although Sr <hi>Francis</hi> would have pocketed it with half that Complement. This Mr
<hi>Bond</hi> being a Gentelman generally beloved, and known all <hi>Paris</hi> over. Theſe
<hi>Benedictines</hi> ſend their ſervant along with him to Mr <hi>Bond;</hi> to whom he firſt delivers his Letter, and then his ſtory and danger deſiring Mr <hi>Bonds</hi> advice and aſſiſtance: which Mr <hi>Bond</hi> (a very Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and Civill Gentelman) readily contributed, and calling ſeverall friends of his together, conſulted what Courſe was beſt to be taken in this buſineſs: And firſt they get printed 300. Bills in the French Tongue, after this manner.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118820:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr William Marriott Marchant of England, at preſent in Paris; prayes all Fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the ſaid Citty, that if any ſhall bring them any Letters of Exchange Drawne from London, or from Roven, payable to him, or elſe from Mris Iean Marriott of London aforeſayd, Wife of the ſayd William Marriott, that they would not pay them, and to detaine thoſe that ſhall bring them; The ſayd Mr Marriott having been ſurpriſed, (not underſtanding the French tongue,) by perſons of ill repute. If they bring ſuch letters, or adviſe, to advertiſe Mr Bond Controller of the Queen of Englands houſe at the Pallace Royall thereof, he will reſolve them of the reaſons: and the diſcoveries ſhall do an acceptable ſervice to the Republique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe bills were (as it were) in an inſtant ſpread throughout all <hi>Paris,</hi> next they goe to ſearch for Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> and with a ſpeciall warrant, and a good guard (which Mr <hi>Bond</hi> eaſily obtained) they finde the houſe, and therein his whore and man that wayted on Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> whom they ſecure: and ſearching the houſe farther for Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> Mr <hi>Marriott</hi> finds his owne ſuit and cloak, and the riding Coat before ſpoken of, which hee takes away with him. And ſeeing Sir <hi>Francis</hi> his Picture, takes that away likewiſe, but no perſonall or reall Sir <hi>Francis</hi> Could be found: therfore they ſecure his man in the <hi>Pallace Royall,</hi> where they detain him ſome 9 or 10 dayes; to ſee if he would diſcover his maſter: But it was more then he could do, but he told that his Maſter was not gone out of the houſe above halfe an hour before they came to ſearch for him. With that Sir <hi>Francis</hi> his Whore and her mother threatned to proſecute Mr
<hi>Marriott</hi> for the lives of their 2 husbands, becauſe they went out of Town together, and they ſwore they had never ſeen them ſince. But Mr <hi>Marriott</hi> having the better end of the ſtaffe, and a friend in Court (Mr <hi>Bond</hi> who would not yet forſake him) ceaſed not to proſecute them ſo cloſe that if they had bin then taken, they had both been hanged: however he was reſolved to try the utmoſt what law would do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; and proſecuted ſo farre, that he might have had their pictures hung up in the market place, and then any man might kill them and have 10 <abbr>lb.</abbr> for his paines. This ſtruck ſuch a terrour in the women, and ſo (by them) ſo frighted their husbands (as they called them,) that then they made friends to Mr <hi>Bond,</hi> (who had the whole management of the buſines) to take up the buſines, before the extreamity of the law ſhould paſſe upon them.</p>
            <p>This was readily agreed unto by Mr <hi>Bond,</hi> in regard this Sir <hi>Francis</hi> was hereby diſcovered to be what he really was not what he ſeemed to be, a Knight, but a Knave, nay a very Rogue, being an <hi>Iriſh man born,</hi> his name <hi>More</hi> (as I ſayd before) and had been an officer in the wars; and had often acted ſuch parts before now, for he had been known twice before to have taken a Religious habit to ſhrowd his Villany in the like Exigents.</p>
            <p>Now as I ſayd, having been a Collonel of the late Kings Army, and there being many ſuch in and about <hi>Paris,</hi> who threatned to be the Death of Mr
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118820:8"/>
               <hi>Marriott,</hi> if he did proceed thus to diſgrace them; Mr
<hi>Marriott</hi> was content, provided, that Sir <hi>Francis</hi> ſhould come and acknowledge his fault, and aſk him forgiveneſs before ſome friends of her Majeſties, whereof Mr
<hi>Bond</hi> was to be one; and then he would freely forgive him. This was agreed to on their part, and the day and hour appointed at the Comiſſaryes houſe: but Sir <hi>Francis alias Coll. Moore</hi> came not, but ſent a meſſenger with his whore to begge his excuſe, and deſire them not to require his preſence at that buſines. But Mr <hi>Marriott</hi> would not conſent to it; either he muſt come himſelf, or elſe he would ſtill proſecute him: ſo at laſt after one or two put offs more, this <hi>Moore alias Barker</hi> comes to the ſtake, and there before all the Company, did acknowledge all this that is written to be true: deſired Mr
<hi>Marriott</hi> and Mr <hi>Bond</hi> to Pardon him; which they did: and Mr <hi>Marriott</hi> not only pardoned theſe injuryes done againſt him, but deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God to pardon him too, forgave him the mony which he had formerly lent him from time to time: and ſo turned him going, to exerciſe the like plotts.</p>
            <p>And ſo returns our ſtory with Mr <hi>Marriott</hi> ſafe into <hi>England,</hi> who is here, and will Juſtify all this to be true. And this ſtory was written by a Gentleman, that was an Ey and ear witneſs of all paſſages in this Relation, and perſonally preſent in all, after Mr <hi>Marriots</hi> return to <hi>Paris:</hi> and ſet forth for a Caution to all Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, Travellers, and others, that they may be armed and prepared to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the treachery and falſehood of him, or any ſuch diſſembling Sycophants.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
